Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. I want to first start by saying
that our thoughts go out to the Bain family and the family
that was to be his prospective in-laws, the Faitelewiczes. I don't know
if people heard, there was a fatal crash up in the Catskills.
Steve Bain, who's and his family long-time resident of Riverdale, his son
Yehuda was in a car with his prospective in-laws and his כלה
kallah and siblings and I don't know what the details were but
there's a terrible crash and Yehuda died, so did the prospective in-laws.
The irony is that the further future father-in-law was going to be
was like a long-time הצלה Hatzalah member and he was involved in
like overseeing emergency services for the area or something.
Really, the World Trade Center,
wow.
So yeah, and the כלה kallah to be and I think is
in serious condition and some of the I think the two brothers
in the car also in serious condition. So our prayers go out
to them and just to the whole family. It was really such
a tremendous tragedy and the funeral's going to be actually for Yehuda's
going to be here in the שול shul at one o'clock today.
So our thoughts are with them.
All right, we resume the דף daf today. It's דף י״ז daf
yud zayin and I believe well I don't know where did we
leave off yesterday? I wasn't here. Are we up to איבעיא isrei
on the top of דף י״ז daf yud zayin or does anybody
remember? Yeah, we're up to איבעיא. isrei. Okay, so we have the
משנה mishna that has the cases that I think some people were
asking about which is a נזיר nazir who's in a cemetery and
he accepts נזירות nezirus upon himself.
Oh, you're a little further down? Okay, fine. All right, well, okay,
so that's a good deal further down. Okay, so anyway, and that
actually is relevant as Michael asked me a few minutes ago to
the question of somebody who accepts נזירות nezirus today. What happens if
somebody is טמא tamei and they accept נזירות? nezirus? What are the
implications of that? And there's a question about when the נזירות nezirus
takes effect. There's also an interesting question which the גמרא Gemara is
going to get to and is getting to but I would just
want to put it on the table about what happens you know
if you're already טמא tamei and you become טמא tamei again. If
it's even like literally the first day you became טמא. tamei. Like
if you could always start talking about if it's the second day
you know I became טמא, tamei, I touched a dead body, so
day two I'm somewhat even if I did nothing I'm already in
the process of becoming טהור tahor because on day three we're able
to sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So if
I were to touch a dead body again on day two I
would restart the clock. It would have some effect. But touching a
body on day one it doesn't seem to have any effect. Okay,
so that's an interesting question if I'm already טמא, tamei, do I
get lashes for becoming טמא tamei again on the very same day?
And that's relevant, I want to put on the table not just
for a נזיר, nazir, it's relevant for a כהן kohen because it's
an interesting question about what is the you know what is the
story about כהנים kohanim nowadays. We assume everybody is טמא מת, tamei
meis, people are born in hospitals where there are morgues. We assume
nowadays that just people can't avoid it. Okay, and if that's true
and a כהן's kohen already טמא, tamei, you know what's the story
about about becoming טמא tamei again? Now again as I just said,
the real question is only the day of. Afterwards, like any day
that's one day later, there tends to be a pretty universal assumption
that that's adding a level of טומאה tumah and therefore it is
equally prohibited. But there is an interesting question the day of and
that's something that's relevant for כהנים. kohanim. So we're not up to
that yet, but I wanted to put that on the table. So
the משנה mishna says that somebody who is in a cemetery who
accepts נזירות nezirut that their נזירות nezirut starts once they leave the
you know once they become טהור. tahor. Okay, they don't bring a
קרבן korban because the קרבן korban for becoming טמא tamei is when
you started as a נזיר טהור nazir tahor and then you became
טמא. tamei. Here where you started as a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei,
you have to become טהור, tahor, you go through the process of
the ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you become טהור tahor
and then your
נזירות nezirus begin, your thirty days begin, but you don't bring a
קרבן. korban. That was the basic point of the משנה, mishna, had
some confusing phrase about עולין לו או אין עולין לו, olin lo
or ein olin lo, but that's the basic point of the משנה.
mishna. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says actually that you would only bring
a קרבן korban if you became טמא tamei the second day of
your נזירות של טהרה. nezirut of tahara. That it says the earlier
days will fall away. So if the question is if you were
a נזיר טהור nazir tahor and became טמא tamei the very day
you became a נזיר, nazir, would you bring a קרבן? korban? That's
a debate. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says only on the second day.
But again the case when a person's in the cemetery becomes a
נזיר, nazir, does not bring a קרבן korban because they started off
the טומאה tumah and their thirty days begins once they become טהור
tahor once they on day seven after they've done the three and
the seven and the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. No
קרבן, korban, none of that special ritual in the תורה Torah of
how a נזיר nazir becomes טהור, tahor, that's not relevant because that's
only for a נזיר nazir that was טהור tahor and became טמא.
tamei. Okay, so this person on day seven. Now the debate of
Thirty days begins once they become טהור, tahor, once they're on day
seven after they've done the three and the seven and the ashes
of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. No קרבן, korban, none of that
special ritual in the תורה Torah of how a נזיר nazir becomes
טהור. tahor. That's not relevant because that's only for a נזיר nazir
that was טהור tahor and became טמא. tamei. Okay, so this person
on day seven. Now, the debate of רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan and
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is about whether the נזירות neziros begins or
does not begin when they're in when he's in the cemetery. Now,
what does exactly that mean? The גמרא's Gemara going to go through
a few iterations. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara first thinks that the
question is whether the prohibitions of נזירות, neziros, you know, will be
will begin or not? Like really, according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish,
as long as you're in a cemetery, nothing has started. So if
the person actually were to drink wine and get a haircut and
you know, leave the cemetery and go back and become טמא tamei
again and so on, they would not get lashes. The prohibitions do
not begin in the state until the person becomes טהור. tahor. In
a state of טומאה, tumah, the prohibitions do not begin, which is
again ironic because if you think about a נזיר טהור nazir tahor
that became טמא, tamei, they're a full נזיר, nazir, right? A person
was a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, they became טמא, tamei, they have
to go through this process, right? Certainly at that stage, if he
drinks wine or shaves or whatever, gets lashes. But somehow at this
stage, I'm just going to give you a hint, a spoiler, the
גמרא's Gemara going to take it back, but at this stage we
think that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is saying that the whole thing
is suspended. If it didn't get a chance to start בטהרה, betaharah,
the whole thing is suspended and the person would still not get
any lashes for any of the transgressions of נזיר. nazir. We're going
to take that back, but that's where we are right now. So
let's take a look.
So we're going to go with the following. You know, let's actually
I know that you got a few lines further, but for my
sake I'm going to start from the איתבי eisvei at the top
of the דף, daf, because that sets the stage. Okay, איתבי, eisvei,
the second the end of the first line of the דף. daf.
אין בין טמא שנזר, ein bein tamei shenazar, nice verb now, שנזר,
shenazar, okay? There's no difference between טמא tamei that became a that
accepted נזירות neziros to נזיר טהור שנטמא, nazir tahor shenitma, as opposed
to a נזיר טהור nazir tahor that became טמא, tamei, אלא, ela,
טמא שנזר, tamei shenazar, here's the difference, a טמא tamei a person
who's טמא tamei who accepted נזירות, neziros, שביעי שלו עולה לו מן
המנין, shevii shelo oleh lo min haminyan, since they just have to
wait till day seven, right? Because they have to become טהור, tahor,
so the day seven they become טהור tahor and that's where the
thirty days
begins. בנזיר טהור שנטמא, benazir tahor shenitma, but a נזיר טהור nazir
tahor that becomes טמא, tamei, you bring a קרבן korban and that
whole ritual of a נזיר טהור nazir tahor who became טמא tamei
beginning again requires not just a טהרה taharah process that ends on
day seven, but a קרבן korban that is brought on day eight.
So for that person, because it requires the קרבן korban and that
whole ritual, the restarting doesn't start again until that that is finished,
until the קרבן, korban, until day eight. אין שביעי שלו עולה לו
מן המנין. ein shevii shelo oleh lo min haminyan. Day seven does
not begin the counting, the counting only begins on day eight. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, ואי סלקא דעתך לא חלה, ve-i salka
dachach lo chalah, according to you ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, that for
the guy who was טמא, tamei, the whole נזירות neziros didn't begin
yet, אמאי עולה לו מן המנין? amai oleh lo min haminyan? Why
does that stay count as part of the as part of the
seven days? What's hold on, I gotta remind myself what that question
is. Because hold on. Wait
a minute.
Why does seventh day count towards the start?
Seventh day is number one of thirty.
Yeah, so why is that a question? Hold on. Sorry.
Oh, I see. So it's not so the question is not so
strong and it's funny that the גמרא Gemara accepts this, because the
גמרא Gemara understands according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish that not just
does the is the נזירות neziros in abeyance because the person did
not get was טמא tamei and therefore could not take effect, it's
so much in abeyance that it won't begin until the person actually
says that it should start now. Okay, because the whole thing was
suspended at the outset, it's not enough that the person becomes טהור,
tahor, the person has to actively say, I'm now beginning it. All
right, so if again, that none of that is in the גמרא,
Gemara, okay, but that's but that's the but based on a different
גמרא, Gemara, that's the supposition that תוספות Tosafos is saying. And therefore
the question is, why does it start automatically for him on day
seven? It shouldn't say that it starts day seven count, it should
say he starts counting when he re- when he begins it, when
he triggers it. All right, not a great question because that whole
assumption is not there. But that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Why does תוספות Tosafos say that that's the question?
Because an earlier תוספות Tosafos discusses why he thinks that he needs
to explicitly trigger it. If you take a look, you want to
see that, he says, hold on.
Okay, if you look at תוספות Tosafos ריש לקיש Resh Lakish on
טז עמוד
ב, tes-zayin amud bais, like a few lines from the bottom, five
lines from the bottom.
ריש לקיש אמר אין נזירות חלה עליו Resh Lakish amar ein neziros
chalah alav
בעודו טמא עד שיטהר be-odo tamei ad she-yit-hare ואז יצטרך לחזור ולקבל
עליו נזירות. ve-az yit-starech lachazor u-lekabel alav neziros. Okay,
so there he says you would have to accept it again. ובקונטרס
פירש דבקבלה מועטת סגי u-vekuntreis peireish de-vekabalah mu'etes sagi לומר יחול עליו
נזירות. lomar yachul alav neziros.
Okay, you don't have to do a real קבלה, kabalah, you just
have to say you're- Beginning. What were you reading Michael? Oh yeah,
this was in the גמרא. Gemara. כמאן דלא אמר מיהא חלה עלי.
k’man d’lo amar meha chala alei.
Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara also wasn’t explicit, but again, it does
sound, yeah, but the גמרא Gemara doesn’t say explicitly that he has
to accept it upon himself. Okay, so again, it’s not clear why
תוספות Tosafot is saying this because other—but maybe otherwise you don’t understand
what’s bothering the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא, Gemara, like, the גמרא Gemara
had a very strange question. According to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, why
do you start on day seven? What do you mean why do
you start on day seven? 'Cause then you’re טהור tahor and then
you start. So תוספות Tosafot has to read in an assumption that
for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, since it’s suspended, it doesn’t begin until
the person will actively trigger it and say that he wants it
to begin now. Okay, so that’s the assumption and the question therefore
is on that—is on that assumption. So let’s see what the גמרא—so
Gemara that seems enough to get the גמרא Gemara to retract itself.
Again, why it couldn’t just retract itself and say you don’t need
to actively trigger it, it takes effect right away, I don’t know,
but let’s see where the גמרא Gemara goes now. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
so says אמר מר בר רב אשי, amar Mar bar Rav Ashi,
מהיכא קאמרת לא פליגי דחייל. Meheicha kaamrat lo pligi d'chayil. You know
what? You're right. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't disagree that the—the idea
that it takes effect even though you're טמא. tamei. Everybody agrees that
even though you're טמא tamei when you begin the נזירות, nezirut, it
takes effect.
אלא כי פליגי למילקי. Ela ki pligi l'milki. The question is, how
weighty is it? If it began בטומאה, b'tumah, do you still get
lashes or not? Okay, so everybody agrees you're a נזיר טמא nazir
tamei right now. You don't bring a קרבן korban again 'cause you
started that way, but because it started this way, in this stage
of טומאה tumah before you become טהור, tahor, will you still get
lashes? Okay, רבי יוחנן סבר כיון דחייל לקי. Rabbi Yochanan savar keivan
d'chayil laki. Look, it took effect, so you get lashes. It’s the
real thing.
Okay. וריש לקיש סבר—ריש לקיש holds—לא לקי. lo laki. No, it does
not, you don't get lashes.
If you become טמא tamei again,
what if you were to become טמא tamei again? But now, again,
if you say if you were to become טמא tamei again you
wouldn't get lashes, that would be the most understandable. The גמרא Gemara
is not yet clear, what about if you were to drink wine?
Would you get lashes? Okay. So but it would be most understandable
for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish to say I can't give you lashes
for becoming טמא tamei if you started off as being טמא. tamei.
Okay. Now, by the way though, again what's important to know is
it's not just because you're already טמא. tamei. It's because the נזירות
nezirut from the outset has not yet become the full-blown נזירות. nezirut.
Right? That's part of the argument. Again, if a נזיר nazir started
as a נזיר טהור nazir tahor and became טמא tamei and now
they have to go through a process of becoming טהור tahor again,
in that stage of a נזיר טמא nazir tamei who started as
טהור, tahor, everybody would agree that the full prohibitions would apply with
lashes and everything. That's when it started properly. The fact that now
you're in a position of טומאה tumah doesn't get you off the
hook for anything. Here, the problem is that it never really started
as a full good נזירות. nezirut. So therefore ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says I'll accept that it took effect in—to some degree, but not
enough that you're going to get lashes. Now, now look—we go to
the—we—get
your—become טהור, tahor, you don't bring a קרבן, korban, you just become
טהור, tahor, get ashes of פרה אדומה, parah adumah, and then you
get into the status of full נזירות. nezirut. But at this stage,
it's somewhat—it's somewhat not full-blown yet. Okay, now—now he doesn't say only—it
could be only for טומאה tumah that it's not full-blown, could be
for everything. Let's take a look. Okay, the גמרא Gemara seems to
say categorically you don't get lashes according to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Eitivei Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan challenged this idea of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. מי
שנזר והוא בבית הקברות, Mi shenazar v'hu b'veit hakevarot, somebody who accepted
נזירות nezirut in a cemetery. אפילו היה שם שלשים יום—this afilu haya
sham shloshim yom is quoting our משנה—even Mishnah if he was there
thirty days. אין עולין לו מן המנין ואינו מביא קרבן טומאה. ein
olin lo min haminyan v'eino meivi korban tumah.
You don't get started with counting, you know, it doesn't matter how
long you're there, your hair could be growing down to your toes,
okay, if you don't become טהור tahor you don't start counting your
thirty days and you don't bring a קרבן korban because a קרבן
korban is only if you were first טהור. tahor. קרבן
טומאה הוא דלא מייתי. Korban tumah hu d'lo maity. So all the
משנה Mishnah says is the one exception to the laws of נזירות
nezirut is that you don't bring a קרבן. korban. That seems to
be the only thing that's being—that's being ruled out here. הוא דלא
מייתי. hu d'lo maity. הא מלקי לקי עליה. ha malki laki aleih.
But it sounds like for all other laws of נזירות, nezirut, it's
a full נזירות nezirut and you get lashes for violating. So that
seems a pretty good—strong argument. What does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. say
back? He'd say the following: בדין הוא דליתני אינו לוקה. B'din hu
d'litni eino lokei. Really it should say you don't get lashes. Okay,
you're right. אלא משום דקבעי למיתני סיפא ela mishum d'kaba'ei lemitni seifa
יצא ונכנס עולה לו מן המנין ומביא קרבן טומאה. yatza v'nichnas oleh
lo min haminyan u'meivi korban tumah. Since the focus of the משנה
Mishnah was to discuss when you would bring a קרבן טומאה, korban
tumah, that if you became טהור tahor and you reentered at that
stage, even on the very same day, you would bring a קרבן
טומאה, korban tumah, okay, which is against רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you need to be on the second day.
And this משנה Mishnah is saying even if you were טמא tamei
and became טהור tahor and on the same day you became טהור
tahor you became טמא tamei again, you still bring a קרבן. korban.
So the focus of the משנה Mishnah is קרבן. korban. So therefore,
תנא רישא
אינו מביא קרבן טומאה. tana reisha eino meivi korban tumah. So the
רישא reisha talks about קרבן טומאה, korban tumah, which is a way
of saying, you know, the focus of this משנה Mishnah is on
when—when do you bring a קרבן טומאה. korban tumah. It's not on
the other question of when do the full laws of נזירות nezirut
apply. All right, nevertheless it's a pretty strong... question. If a guy
in a
cemetery is, does you know his נזירות nezirus is so so sort
of compromised that he's not going to get lashes for transgressing, you
would think that a משנה Mishna talking about that scenario would mention
it. Okay, but nevertheless ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's defense is the משנה
Mishna is only interested in this קרבן korban question. It's not interested
in the transgression and in the lashes question.
Wait, so according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish guy's in the cemetery,
declares נזירות, nezirus, yeah, and then has a glass of wine, yeah,
in the cemetery,
right, it's not מותר, muttar, but he wouldn't get lashes.
He would not,
right, because the נזירות nezirus has not taken effect yet in its
full form.
But according to the other position
he would, yeah, totally,
he would get lashes for drinking that glass of wine.
Exactly, exactly. So that's what the רבנן Rabbanan is saying, if there's
this huge difference from this guy and the normal נזיר, nazir, the
משנה Mishna should have mentioned it. And ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's answer
is yeah, the משנה Mishna was only interested in the קרבן korban
question. Okay, we're not talking about all this other stuff, which is
huge, right? All right, so let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
Narrowly, yeah. Okay, so it says like this, תא שמע: Ta shema:
אין
בין
נזיר טמא שנדר לנזיר טהור שנטמא אלא, Ein bein nazir tamei shenadar
lenazir tahor shenitma ella, there so this is the ברייתא braisa we
quoted at the top of the דף, daf, when it we thought
it was ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's even a broader statement that it
didn't even you didn't even begin to be a נזיר nazir till
afterwards. So there's no difference between somebody who is טמא tamei who
accepted נזירות nezirus versus somebody who is טהור tahor became a נזיר
nazir and then became טמא, tamei, אלא שטמא שנדר שביעי שלו עולה
לו מן המנין, ella shetamei shenadar shevii shelo oleh lo min haminyan,
but the guy who started off as טמא tamei doesn't bring קרבן
korban and since he doesn't bring a קרבן, korban, he becomes טהור
tahor on day seven and therefore his נזירות nezirus of thirty days
of טהרה tahara begins on day seven.
ונזיר טהור שנטמא, V'nazir tahor shenitma, but the guy who was טהור
tahor became טמא, tamei, he has to not only become טהור tahor
on day seven but bring a קרבן korban on day eight. So
that guy אין שביעי שלו עולה לו מן המנין, ein shevii shelo
oleh lo min haminyan, he doesn't get to start counting on day
seven because he has to wait till day eight till that process
is done. That's the only difference. הא למלקות, Ha l'malkus, so if
that's the only difference, when do you start restart the נזירות nezirus
or when do you start the נזירות nezirus of טהרה, tahara, it
sounds like you know there's no other difference. So according to you,
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, there's a huge area of difference whether you
get lashes on transgression during this time. הא למלקות זה וזה שוין,
Ha l'malkus zeh v'zeh shavin, it would sound like for lashes they
would exactly be the same, right? All it says is the difference
is whether you start on day seven or day eight. אמר לך,
Amar lach, לא, lo, ותגלחת
זה וזה שוין. v'tiglachas zeh v'zeh shavin. When it comes to shaving,
they are the same. We'll get back to that phrase in a
minute. אבל לענין מלקות מאי? Aval l'inyan malkus mai? So what do
you want to say though? Well you want to say that when
it comes to lashes, there is this huge difference? זה לוקה וזה
אינו לוקה? Zeh lokeh v'zeh eino lokeh? That you so you do
want to concede that when it comes to lashes, that there actually
is this huge difference between them, that the guy who started off
as טמא tamei doesn't get lashes? לתנייה? Litnyei? So if there is
still that huge difference, I'm going to get back to the word
of תגלחת tiglachas in a minute, but if there is this huge
difference about lashes, why not say it? גמרא Gemara says בתקנתא קא
מיירי בכולהי לא קא מיירי. B'takanata ka mairi b'kulei lo ka mairi.
What we're talking about is how the נזיר nazir gets back on
track. We're not talking about transgression. Okay, when we say there's no
difference between the guy who started טמא tamei and the guy who
became טמא, tamei, we don't want to talk about somebody sinning. We're
not talking about the we're not talking about people who sin. We're
not talking about they became טמא tamei and now how do they
become a good נזיר nazir and get on track? Okay, and one
guy he starts on day seven and the other guy starts on
day eight. We're not talking about sin. We're not talking we're not
going there. Okay, another way of saying that's not the interest of
this ברייתא, braisa, but here made a little bit clearer, right, by
saying like you know we're not interested right now in talking about
transgression, about what what would be the consequences of transgressing your נזירות.
nezirus. We're talking about how one get you know does the נזירות
nezirus properly. That's the focus and therefore we didn't get into that
area. Okay, it could be differences there. Yeah, when you get to
the question of transgression, there could be huge differences, which ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish, would say there would be, but that's not our interest.
Our interest is not the consequences of transgression, our interest is in
how to do a proper נזירות nezirus and therefore one starts on
day seven, one starts on day eight. Now I want to do
two things to say two things. First, what I've been bracketing but
I'll say it now is the idea that he starts on day
seven also should not be taken totally for granted, even though he
doesn't have to bring a קרבן korban so you say he's טהור
tahor on day seven because even on day seven somebody who was
טמא מת tamei meis does not become fully טהור tahor until nightfall.
They're considered a טבול יום. tvul yom. It's a process that ended
with going to the מקוה mikvah and and you go to the
מקוה mikvah and then the full טהרה tahara comes at nightfall. Okay,
but nevertheless the it's only a very residual טומאה tumah for certain
הלכות halachos of entering into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay, but
not for anything else. So תוספות Tosafos just points out that residual
טומאה tumah that's after you go to the מקוה mikvah would not
be contrary to the concept of נזירות nezirus and the נזירות nezirus
would be able to begin after the person went to the מקוה,
mikvah, but just to be aware there is even a little element
of חידוש chiddush here in day seven. Let's get back to that
phrase about saying the גמרא Gemara says look, but for shaving they're
the same. Okay, there's still a difference of of lashes, but they're
the same, the guy who started
טמא. tamei. What does that mean? So take a look at תוספות.
Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says two very interesting different interpretations. תוספות לא הלא
תגלחת זה וזה שוין, Tosafot lo halo tiglachas ze ve-ze shavin, five
lines down in the wide lines, תוספות Tosafot says the following: יש
מפרשים דלקי אחי תגלחת, Yesh mefarshim dilki achi tiglachas, that here saying
they're the same when it comes to shaving means whether he started
טמא Tamei or whether he became טמא Tamei they would still get
lashes for shaving. That רש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying that you
don't get lashes only refers—Michael here's the point, your point—only refers to
if you became טמא Tamei you wouldn't get lashes. If you started
טמא Tamei you can't get lashes again for becoming טמא Tamei until
you actually start the נזירות Nezirut full. Now again don't confuse any
of this with the guy who started טהור Tahor and became טמא.
Tamei. That person gets full lashes for everything even if he's טמא
Tamei now. This is—anyway this is the guy though he started טמא,
Tamei, so it started compromised, it's not full. So that's where רש
לקיש Reish Lakish says he might not get lashes. So here's the
question: might not get lashes for anything? Or might not get lashes
just for becoming טמא? Tamei? That's the particular aspect that's already that's
been started off compromised. So תוספות Tosafot says that might be what
the גמרא Gemara means. The גמרא Gemara might be saying: you know
what? Actually it is the same when it comes to issues of
shaving that you get lashes. The only difference רש לקיש Reish Lakish
was saying was about lashes for becoming טמא Tamei if it started
off as being טמא. Tamei. That's one answer. And then it would
also include drinking wine. So that's one answer that might be what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. But then let's see what תוספות Tosafot
says: ולא נהירא, Ve-lo nehira, that does not seem to be the
right interpretation. דלימא לתגלחת ויין זה וזה שוין. Dilayma le-tiglachas ve-yayin ze
ve-ze shavin. So if it really meant for the parts that weren't
טומאה Tumah it shouldn't just have mentioned shaving, it should say for
shaving and for wine you get lashes. And all רש לקיש Reish
Lakish was saying is you don't get lashes for becoming טמא. Tamei.
כיון דבאיסור תגלחת קמיירי, Keivan de-bisur tiglachas kamayri, if you're talking about
the prohibition of shaving. לכן נראה לי, Lachen nireh li, therefore it
seems to
me, says תוספות, Tosafot, הלא לתגלחת פירוש למצות תגלחת לעניין שמגלח בשביעי
לטהרה. Halo le-tiglachas perush le-mitzvas tiglachas le-inyan she-megalayach be-shvi'i le-tahara. So what
we're going to introduce in a few minutes is the idea that
the guy who started טמא Tamei doesn't bring a קרבן Korban and
becomes טהור Tahor on day seven. But for a נזיר Nazir who
became טמא Tamei to start again he's got to do two things:
he's got to bring a קרבן Korban and shave his hair. And
somehow restart. Okay, so the question here is the guy who started
off as טמא Tamei and he started no קרבן Korban and he
starts counting on day seven, does he still have the ritual of
shaving the hair? Now that seems very bizarre. You would think if
you're in that whole category of bringing a קרבן Korban the shaving
of the hair is part of that ritual, right? If this guy
doesn't do the קרבן Korban maybe he shouldn't do the shaving at
all. But or you would think he wouldn't do the shaving at
all. But the גמרא Gemara is going to raise that question in
a minute. Okay so here what the way תוספות Tosafot is reading
is what the גמרא Gemara is saying is: no, no, no. Since
again remember the גמרא Gemara said we're not interested in the transgression
in this ברייתא, Braisa, we're interested in how the guy gets back
on track. So it's say one guy starts on seven, one guy
starts on eight, and maybe they're all in other ways they're similar.
What does it mean in other ways they're similar? Well they both
have to shave. One guy on day seven, one guy on day
eight, that we haven't discussed that yet but that's what רש לקיש
Reish Lakish is arguing right now. That's about them getting back on
track. But we're not talking about transgression. Okay and transgression there would
be a huge difference and even whether it be טומאה Tumah or
shaving or wine רש לקיש Reish Lakish would say if you started
off compromised you're not until it becomes full you're not going to
get lashes for any of those. Okay so two very different reads
of the גמרא Gemara whether רש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying you
only don't get lashes for becoming טמא, Tamei, that's the particular thing
that's compromised, or whether he's saying you don't get lashes for anything
until you know until it actually becomes
full.
Okay yes. Why would if there is a distinction being made between
somebody who becomes טומאה Tumah intentionally and somebody when a body drops
dead next to you?
Yes we're actually going to get to that right in a minute
that there is a
difference. You certainly don't receive lashes if it's אונס, Ones, if it's
against you know or even if it's negligent you don't receive lashes.
Lashes is only if it's you know if it's intentional. But there
are going to be another difference in a minute whether it's an
אונס Ones or not which we'll get to.
Yes. It sounds—I had been learning this as a type of like
שבת לשון, Shabbas lashon, right, פטור אבל אסור. Patur aval assur. How
come they don't
consider—in other words a תגלחת? Tiglachas? In other words it's אסור Assur
but you don't—well that
is what רש לקיש Reish Lakish would say: לא לקי Lo laki
but you would still get—it would still be forbidden.
So it's the same type of—it's not the lashes.
Yeah even when the גמרא Gemara is suggesting that רש לקיש Reish
Lakish according to רש לקיש Reish Lakish that you don't or say
interpreting רש לקיש Reish Lakish that you don't get lashes he's not
saying it's מותר Muttar to do it, right? That's why the גמרא
Gemara can say we're not talking about transgression. Even for רש לקיש
Reish Lakish it's transgressive it's just you wouldn't get lashes. Okay but
now the גמרא Gemara is going to completely sort of you know
put the final like you know end to this and it says
the following. תא
שמע Ta shema come and hear, מי שהיה טמא ונזר, Mi shehaya
tamei ve-nazar, if somebody who was טמא Tamei and accepted נזירות, Nezirut,
אסור לגלח ולשתות יין, Assur legaleiach velishtos yayin, you can't shave or
drink wine,
ואם גילח. Ve-im gilach. shaved or drank wine or became טמא tamei
*tamei*, הרי זה סופג ארבעים *harei zeh sofeig arba'im*, you get forty
lashes. Okay, it’s very explicit. Even if you accept נזירות neziros *nezirut*
בטומאה *betuma*, you are forbidden to do anything, and if so, you
get lashes. תיופתא *Tiyufta*. Alright, well that sort of ends, right, so
that sort of ends that. That’s a direct contradiction to ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*. Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* gave a weak
answer to that yesterday and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* discusses why that weak
answer wouldn’t work here. You can take a look at תוספות *Tosafos*,
but basically the simple sense of this ברייתא braisa, *braisa* is really
completely against ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. It’s clear that the full טומאה
tumah *tuma* begins, the full נזירות neziros *nezirut* begins even though you
don’t start counting until you become טהור tahor *tahor*.
Yes, they could have brought this ברייתא braisa *braisa* sooner.
Oh, but then it wouldn’t have been any fun. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, so that’s not the first time we’ve had a couple of
these discussions where like,
yeah, it’s a very clear ברייתא Baraisa *braisa* at the end.
Okay, does תא שמע Ta shema, *Ta shma* always introduce a תנאידיק
*Tanaidic* source?
I’m pretty positive, I mean I can’t say there’s not one exception
in ש"ס *Shas*.
So you don’t, you’re not going to have a, like, a תניא
*Tanya*?
No, no, no.
תא שמע *Ta shma*, right, right.
It’s a way
but with a particular function in the, exactly.
Okay, בעי רבא *Ba'ei Rava*, רבא *Rava* asked. Okay, so we settled
that. Guy’s טמא tamei *tamei*, accepts נזירות neziros *nezirut*, full נזיר Nazir,
*nazir*, you just don’t start counting yet, which is clearly the sense
of all the תנאידיק *Tanaidic* material. The only difference is when, is
that you don’t bring a קרבן korban, *korban* and when you start
counting. Do you count on day seven because you didn’t bring a
קרבן korban, *korban*, or if you started טהור tahor. *tahor* and became
טמא tamei, *tamei*, you have to bring a קרבן korban *korban* and
you start on day eight. Everything else is the exact same in
terms of prohibitions and whatnot. So we still have to ask some
other questions. בעי רבא *Ba'ei Rava*, so רבא *Rava* asked, נזיר Nazir
*nazir* or נזר *nazar* והוא בבית הקברות *vehu beveit hakevarot*, מהו *mahu*?
If somebody was a נזיר Nazir *nazir* or took נזירות neziros *nezirut*,
depends on the גרסה *girsa* here, and in the cemetery, what’s the
story? בעי שהייה למלקות או לא Bay' shehiya l'malkus o lo? *Ba'ei
shehiya lemalkus o lo*? Do you have to wait, tarry, in order
to get lashes or not? Now here’s the model, here’s the model
that רבא *Rava* has in mind. Okay, the model that רבא *Rava*
has in mind is the following: if you’re in a בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, okay, you’re a כהן *kohen* let’s say, or
whatever, whoever, you’re in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. It’s
אסור *assur* to be טמא tamei *tamei* in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, any type of טומאה tumah *tuma*, if you’re actually
in the, you know, עזרה *Azara* itself. Okay, and it’s get lashes
depending on how, whatever, different degrees. Anyway, you get lashes and so
on. You’re there, you’re being totally innocent, and accidentally you trip on
a, or here’s a good example, on a שרץ sheretz *sheretz*. Or
here’s a good example: somebody שחט's *shachts* the animal wrong and it
becomes a נבילה *neveila*. Okay, so and you touch the animal, right?
So you’re טמא tamei *tamei*. Okay, now, do you get lashes? Well,
you didn’t do anything wrong. It was all, you know, it was
all like act of God, well, actually, but anyway, it was unintentional,
okay, it was complete accident, you didn’t do anything wrong. When would
you get lashes at that stage? If somebody said, you’re טמא tamei
*tamei* buddy, you can’t stay here, you gotta leave, and you stayed
around. So your act of staying is considered to be טמא tamei.
*tamei*, actively being טמא tamei. *tamei* in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beis Hamikdash*, like an act of entering almost the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* is your act of staying. So here’s the question
about the נזיר Nazir, *nazir*. The נזיר Nazir, *nazir* is in the
בית הקברות beis hakavaros *Beis Hakevarot*. Okay, if somebody says, buddy, you
better get out, and you stay, is your staying the same in
order to get lashes? Now the first point is, well, one minute,
like why would you need to stay? The very fact that you
willfully accepted נזירות nezirus *nezirut* in the בית הקברות beis hakavaros, *Beis
Hakevarot* is itself a, you know, is itself an act that’s deserving
of lashes. Okay, so you could say, well, I don’t know, maybe
you didn’t realize it was a בית הקברות Beis Hakvaros *Beis Hakevarot*,
you could say you were standing on a grave and you didn’t
realize it, right, and maybe I don’t know if that would be
like a שוגג *shogeig*, it wouldn’t be מזיד *meizid* but it wouldn’t
be a total אונס onus. *oness*, you could have paid more attention.
That could be one scenario. But anyway, but we have to set
up what is the case where you have not transgressed yet and
the only question is would you transgress by your continued staying? Now
another important point that I have to put out there that’s developed
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, there’s a parallel גמרא gemara *Gemara* that
discusses this in שבועות *Shavuos* where it focuses it from the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* perspective, is it wouldn’t matter if you
didn’t get lashes for the original act. The whole discussion of staying
is only an issue when it starts off באונס b'onus? *be'oness*, it
starts off out of your control. So let’s say I intentionally accepted
נזירות nezirus. *nezirut* במזיד *bemeizid* in the בית הקברות Beis Hakvaros. *Beis
Hakevarot*, okay, but nobody was around there to tell me don’t accept
נזירות nezirus *nezirut*, you’re going to be transgressing the minute you start
to be a נזיר Nazir, *nazir*, nobody told me that. So I
didn’t get lashes, right? I mean, God’s going to hold me accountable,
but I get off the hook for lashes, nobody warned me. Interestingly,
I cannot also now get lashes for staying. Because since the initial
act was the willful act, then we can’t—we don’t look at the
more trivial point of staying, the less significant, I shouldn’t say trivial,
of staying as an act. The first act was the act, anything
else doesn’t count, okay? So the only way that staying can count
as the act of transgression, of being in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, of becoming טמא tamei *tamei*, is when the first
act... The first act was not significant. The first act was unintentional.
Okay. So if I didn't realize I was in a cemetery, or
we're going to have another case in the גמרא, gemara or the
animal dropped dead on me in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, therefore
the act being טמא tamei initially, that was not the act. That
was out of my hands. That was not something I did willfully.
So now the focus is: can the tarrying be the act? All
right.
So the לשון lashon of בעי שהייה bay' shehiya means must we
take the שהייה shehiya into account in these circumstances?
No, in order to get lashes, do you need tarrying? Well, let's
take a look. Because we'll see what the
let's see the גמרא. gemara Well, because since I've set it up
for cause I've already anticipated, I've set it up that you're not
liable for anything that preceded. So right. But okay. But that's I'm
just jumping ahead. So let's take a look. נזיר הוא בבית הקברות
מהו? Nazir hu b'veis hakavaros, mahu? בעי שהייה shehiya. למלקות או לא?
Lo, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא דאמרי ליה, Ileima
d'amri lei, "לא תנזור," lo tinzor, people said to him, "don't become
a נזיר, Nazir you're in a cemetery." So he said, "I don't
care." So למה ליה שהייה? lamah lei shehiya? Then who cares whether
it's about the tarrying? The act of becoming a נזיר Nazir, is
itself the act of violating. So נזיר מאי טעמא לא בעי שהייה?
Nazir mai taama lo bay' shehiya? דקא מתרי ביה. d'ka masri bei.
Why does a normal נזיר Nazir who say why do you tell
a normal נזיר, Nazir "don't enter into the בית הקברות"? beis hakevaros,
He doesn't have to wait in the cemetery, he just enters and
transgresses. Why? They warned him. They warned him and he did a
willful act. He walked into the cemetery. So הכי נמי קא מתרי
ביה. hachi nami ka masri bei. Here they warned him, "don't become
a נזיר," Nazir and he did that willful act. That's the violation.
When somebody is doing a willful violation, you do not need שהייה.
The act of entering into the cemetery if you're already a נזיר,
nazir or becoming a נזיר nazir if you're already in the cemetery,
is the willful act of violation. What? מלקות malkus always needs
warning. Right. אלא כגון, Ela k'gon, so
here's the case of אונס. Now I thought I gave an easy
case, which is he didn't realize he was standing on a grave.
But maybe because it says בית הקברות, beis hakevaros, a cemetery, so
we don't have what's an example that not just you're on a
grave, but you're in a cemetery and you became טמא tamei. באונס?
b'onus. What would be that example? How could you not know? כגון
שנכנס בשידה תיבה ומגדל, k'gon she'nichnas b'shidah teivah u'migdal,
you're being brought in in some type of a sealed box. Okay,
like the cat in the hat or something. Doesn't he come out
of a box? What? Oh, that's thing one and thing two. I
don't know. Anyway, yes. He's being transported, right? Right, you're being transported
into but it's a sealed box on the top.
He said that.
But no, but okay, but what you have to understand is it's
also covered on the top. Okay? Okay, it's true, if there's no
overhang, you probably don't have to be covered on the top, only
on the bottom. But we're assuming that there's also trees and whatnot,
so it's basically covered on the top and the bottom. And it's
a type of thing that's so big that it can't become טמא,
tamei. because if it's a smaller thing, then it would itself become
טמא tamei, and טומאה tuma would come in. So you're in your
own little protected אוהל ohel in the cemetery. Okay.
Thing one and
thing two? Yes, I did. ובא חברו, u'va chaveiro,
that's in רש״י. Rashi. ובא חברו, u'va chaveiro,
and your friend comes, not much of a friend, okay? ופרע מעליו
מעזיבה. u'para me'alav maziva.
He tore the top off! Okay? So he made you טמא tamei.
באונס. b'onus? There you are, poof, you became טמא tamei, in the
cemetery against your will. You had thought you had the whole thing
worked out, okay? And you became טמא. tamei. Now somebody says, "Better
get out, or you're because you're transgressing, you're a נזיר," nazir, and
you wait around. Okay? So does the act of waiting around make
you liable for מלקות, malkus, now that you became, got into this
situation באונס? Does the act now become the act of waiting? That
becomes the act. Okay, so what do we say? כי גמרינן שהייה
בבית המקדש אבל אבראי לא. ki gamrinan shehiya b'veis hamikdash, aval a'barai
lo.
When is this idea of tarrying? When it comes to the issue
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash but not outside the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash I will tell you in a minute. אודלמא, od dilma,
or do we say, לא שנא, lo shna, it doesn't matter, tarrying
is like the act of transgressing and it doesn't matter בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, or for the נזיר nazir and it's not and therefore
you'd be liable here too. And the גמרא gemara says תיקו. teiku.
Good question, we don't know. Okay. Now I want to say something
about this issue about the difference of in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and out. From the simple sense, it sounds like it's like
I don't know, just something like "okay, this is a חידוש chiddush
and you can't apply it elsewhere." A special דין din of the
בית המקדש. But there's something I think much more profound going on
here. And that is,
if I
am goes back to the point I said before, of what am
I doing wrong if I am already טמא. tamei, If I am,
let's start with the בית המקדש. Okay, if I'm טמא tamei, and
I'm in the בית המקדש, staying in the בית המקדש is continuing
to do a problem. It's leaving טומאה tuma me, leaving a טמא
tamei? person in the בית המקדש where he doesn't belong, right? That's
what I'm doing by staying. So the fact that I'm not leaving
is I'm continuing to violate the קדושה kedusha of the בית המקדש,
right? That's sort of the problem. So the question is how do
you look at the status of being a נזיר nazir staying around
in the cemetery? He's not violating the status of the cemetery. The
question is, does staying in the cemetery continue to violate his status?
That's a little bit different, right? It's not like there's an object
here that doesn't belong and this object has to get out. I
mean that's sort of the way you could say. The נזיר nazir
is the object. But he's the קדושה. kedusha. He's the קדושה. kedusha.
Right. Exactly. That is exactly. Exactly. The בית הקברות beis hakevaros. is
the dead animal and he's the מקדש. Mikdash. So does,
right. Exactly. So, you know, so that seems to be the question.
Does the fact that this מקדש Mikdash is violating the קדושה kedusha
status and it has to be removed and it's moved by him
removing? But again, who's the object and who's the subject sort of
switches and that might be part of the issue. Yes.
Who makes it something like this happen like in a מקדש? Mikdash?
You don't make the מקדש Mikdash טהור tahor again, right?
You just like, right, get the
טומאה tuma, out.
Right. Get the טומאה tuma out.
Whereas here, right, he doesn't become more טמא. tamei Like you could
see that like why would, why would staying, right?
And that's the other point, excellent, which is the point I said
is that is that the מקדש, Mikdash, right, it's while there's a
problem with the presence of טומאה, tumah its קדושה kedusha doesn't become
violated and compromised, or it doesn't, you don't have to be מטהר
metaher it. It doesn't become טמא. tamei It might be violated, but
you don't have to be מטהר, metaher, no, certain vessels get touched,
but not the מקדש Mikdash as a whole. Okay. So therefore, right,
you can say that it's at full level of קדושה kedusha and
this continued presence is a continued violation. Whereas here, the guy, once
he's already טמא, he, his קדושה kedusha is compromised. He's like a
נזיר טמא. Nazir tamei. Right? The very thing that was holy became
טמא. So maybe, maybe when you leave, you can't go back in,
but maybe staying in isn't a continued violation. So I think that
there are both, exactly, so thank you, that was exactly the other
point that I was going to, that I was thinking about, which
is that here, what are you doing wrong by staying in? There's
something clearly more wrong by keeping טומאה tumah in the בית המקדש
than by keeping a נזיר nazir in a בית הקברות. beis hakevaros
His, his קדושה kedusha has already been compromised. Okay, so who's the
subject, who's the object, who's the קדוש, kadosh, who's the טמא, and
has the קדושה kedusha been compromised or not, or been
נטמא, nitma, that is actually a major difference. So I think it's
a fascinating question.
Yes, you do, so you do have the concept of חיטוי המזבח
chittui hamizbeiach and that the מקדש Mikdash can be מקבל טומאה? mekabel
tuma? Yeah, but not that happens as a
result of this, other, in other, in other words, not that happens
as a result of this dead שרץ sheretz, here.
It's not,
it is בו ביום. bo bayom.
All right, but not, but yes, but not in the, but not
that keeping this שרץ, sheretz you know, that this שרץ already has
changed the status of the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay. Yes.
We had that in the first 30 days. So what? That might
reflect on...
I'm sorry, what?
We had the earlier משנה mishna who stays for 30 days. Right.
So that must reflect on the idea of what you're saying about
the...
Yeah, I mean the משנה mishna doesn't discuss the problem of staying,
and that's the question being raised, but right. Yeah, but yes, I
mean it sort of recognizes that you could, that possible, that you
could stay for a long period of time.
Something might mitigate the idea of that it's increasing.
Right. Right. That's increasing some problem. Yeah, I think that, yes, I
agree. To me, it's much more obvious, it's not just a technical
issue of inside and outside. It's much more obvious that in the
מקדש, Mikdash, it's like this on, this like ongoing violation that's occurring.
Okay, בעי רב אשי, Ba'ei Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi
asks: נזיר והוא בבית הקברות, Nazir vehu beveis hakvaros, so a guy
took נזירות nezirus and he's in the cemetery, טעון גילוח או לאו?
teun giluach o lav? Now this is the question that I mentioned
in passing before. Day seven, he's going to restart because he comes
טהור. tahor We've already said no קרבן, korban. but how about the
ritual of shaving that restarts the נזירות nezirus of טהרה? tahara? Is
that totally part of the קרבן, korban, or is that anytime you
need to become טהור tahor. and restart? Like this time when you
started off as טמא. Okay? So כי בעית גילוחת טהור שנטמא? Ki
ba'it gilochat tahor shenitma? When you need the shaving, somebody who's טהור
tahor. became
טמא, דקא מטמי מנזירותיה, deka mitamei minezirosei, because the נזירות nezirus. has
been violated and became טמא, it was טהור. tahor And the real
point is, and because you're bringing a קרבן korban. and it's part
of the ritual of bringing a קרבן. korban. אבל טמא שנזר לאו?
Aval tamei shenazar lav? But not somebody who's already טמא? או דילמא
לא שנא? O dilma lo shana? Or maybe it doesn't matter? Maybe
even without a קרבן, korban. this is what you do to restart
the נזירות nezirus of טהרה? tahara? תא שמע, come and hear. מי
שנזר והוא בבית הקברות, Mi shenazar vehu beveis hakvaros, אפילו היה שם
שלושים יום, afillu haya sham sheloshim yom, our משנה, mishna, even though
you're there 30 days, אין עולה לו מן המנין, ein oleh lo
min haminyan, and you don't start counting, ואינו מביא קרבן טומאה, ve'eino
meivi korban tuma, and you don't bring a קרבן טומאה korban tuma
because you never started off as טהור. tahor. קרבן טומאה הוא דלא
מייתי, Korban tuma hu dela meisi, so it sounds like the only
difference is the
קרבן. korban, אבל גילוח בעא? Aval gilucha ba'ei? But maybe you have
to shave? It didn't say you don't shave, it just says you
don't bring a קרבן. korban. לא, the גמרא Gemara says no. מה
טעם קאמר? Ma ta'am ka'amar? What's the reason, or meaning I would
say not what's the reason, but like it's all part of the
same package. מה טעם אינו מביא קרבן טומאה? Ma ta'am eino meivi
korban tuma? Why are you not bringing a קרבן טומאה? korban tuma?
משום דלא בעי גילוח, Mishum dela ba'ei giluach, because you don't have
to shave. I would sort of put it the other way: why
do you not shave? Because you don't bring a קרבן. korban, But
the point is, it's all implied. If you're not bringing a קרבן,
you're not doing the shaving that's part of bringing a קרבן. Okay,
so yes, you can't say. The משנה mishna. *Mishnah* only mentions קרבן
*korban*, it's a package. תא שמע *Ta shma*, come and hear.
Just the גילוח מצוה *gilu'ach mitzvah* is...
Yeah, that does to restart it.
תוספות *Tosafot* was...
Exactly, exactly, that comes to restart it. תא שמע *Ta shma*, אין
בין טמא נזיר nazir לנזיר טהור שנטמא *ein bein tamei nazir l'nazir
tahor she'nitma*, there's no difference between again somebody who's טמא *tamei* who
accepts it and somebody who's טהור *tahor* and then becomes טמא *tamei*,
אלא טמא נזיר nazir שביעית שלו עולה מן המנין *ela tamei nazir
shvi'it shelo ola min haminyan*, but the טמא *tamei* guy it starts
on day seven because he didn't need the קרבן *korban*, ונזיר טהור
שנטמא אין שביעית שלו עולה מן המנין *v'nazir tahor she'nitma ein shvi'it
shelo ola min haminyan*, and the guy who was טהור *tahor* and
became טמא *tamei*, you don't start restart on day seven cause you
need the קרבן *korban* on day eight. מאי לאו *Mai lav*, so
it says the only difference, day seven and day eight, and implicitly
the קרבן *korban* that goes with it. But הא לתגלחת *ha l'tiglachat*,
the shaving aspect to restart the טהרה taharah? *tahara*, זה וזה שוים
*ze v'ze shavin*, they'd be the same? So the גמרא *Gemara* says
לא *lo*, no. היכא דקאמר זה וזה שוים *heicha d'ka'amar ze v'ze
shavin*, going back to the point we proved on the עמוד א'
*amud aleph*, transgression and getting lashes, they'd be the same. Okay, but
in terms of the shaving, that you need to maybe there would
be that would be a difference that's wrapped up in the difference
of the קרבן *korban*. So the גמרא *Gemara* is still isn't happy.
אבל תגלחת tiglachas מאי *Aval tiglachat mai*, what are you trying to
say? That when it comes to the idea of shaving, זה מגלח
וזה אינו מגלח *ze m'gale'ach v'ze eino m'gale'ach*, one guy would shave,
the guy who's bringing the קרבן *korban*, and the guy who's not
would not bring the shave? So לתנייה *lisnaye*, so how could you
leave that off? It should be taught. How by you know how
could you say that that's not a difference if it or that
that is a difference, if it was a difference, it needed to
have been said. גמרא *Gemara* says no, תנא שביעית שלו בכל מילי
*tana shvi'it shelo b'chol mili*. No, that's implicit. If you say it
starts on day seven, it means you don't have everything that comes
along with day eight. What's day eight? Day eight is the קרבן
*korban* and the shaving. It's saying that this guy doesn't need that
whole set whole ritual. This guy just starts on day seven without
a קרבן *korban* without a shaving. Okay, תא שמע *Ta shma*, let's
try and prove it again. אין לי אלא ימי טומאתו *Ein li
ela y'mei tumato*, now we're going to get into a new area
which is something we've seen before but new to this discussion, is
the idea that when a נזיר nazir *nazir* is a מצורע metzora?
*metzora*, right, and a טמא *tamei* as a מצורע metzora מוחלט *metzora
muchlat*, as a full מצורע metzora *metzora*, the period of being a
מצורע metzora, *metzora* puts the נזירות nezirus *nezirut* on hiatus. So the
guy was ten days a נזיר nazir *nazir*, became a מצורע metzora.
*metzora*, okay, so then that's going to be a process he has
to go through and the כהן *kohen* comes back or whatever gets
shut up seven days however long that takes during that entire period
he is not counting towards the days of טהרה *tahara* but he
doesn't lose the ten days the days of נזירות nezirus, *nezirut*, I'm
glad I should have said טהרה *tahara*, the days of נזירות nezirus
*nezirut*, but he does not lose the ten days he already banked.
Why? Because he didn't become טמא מת *tamei meit*. A נזיר nazir
*nazir* only the only thing that contradicts his נזירות nezirus *nezirut* is
טומאת מת tumas meis, *tumat meit*, טומאה tumah, *tumah* with dead bodies.
Okay, so because he did not become טמא מת *tamei meit* even
though he's a מצורע metzora, *metzora*, he can't he didn't lose those
earlier days.
He can be a שוכן
*shochen* no problem all day. Exactly. Okay so those ten days normally
a שוכן *shochen* doesn't become טמא *tamei* only if it's a נבילה
*neveila*. Okay right anyway those ten days are still safe. He finishes
being a מצורע metzora. *metzora* and then he goes back and counts
twenty more days. Now I should say there's a little bit of
a problem here because what one thing a מצורע metzora *metzora* has
to do to become טהור *tahor* is, any guess? Shave. So then
you get to the question of can you become a נזיר nazir
*nazir* without having thirty days of hair growth, right? So even if
he doesn't need thirty days for the counting, right, okay let's not
worry about that right now but that's the basic idea. The period
of being a מצורע metzora *metzora* puts the נזירות neziros *nezirut* on
hiatus. You don't lose the earlier days but you don't have but
you don't
count those days either, it puts it on hiatus. So this ברייתא
Baraisa *baraita* is going to try to prove that point. Let's take
a look. And then we'll see how it's relevant for our discussion.
תא שמע *Ta shma*. אין לי אלא ימי טומאתו שאין עולין לו
מן המנין *Ein li ela y'mei tumato she'ein olin lo min haminyan*.
All I know is when a נזיר nazir, *nazir* is טמא *tamei*
that they don't count towards his thirty days. ימי חלוטו yimei chaluto,
*Y'mei chaluto*, when he is sealed off, which is the phrase of
somebody who's a full מצורע metzora, *metzora*, מנין *minayin*, how do I
know that you can't count those days for being a נזיר nazir
*nazir*? Taking for granted that they do not destroy the earlier days
because you didn't become טמא מת *tamei meit*. Only טמא מת *tamei
meit* would lose the earlier days. But how do I know you
can't count those days? ודין הוא *V'din hu*, and it makes sense.
מה ימי טומאה tumah, מגלח ומביא קרבן *Ma y'mei tumah m'gale'ach u'meivi
korban*, the same way when a נזיר nazir. *nazir* is טמא *tamei*,
look there's an analogy between the cases, how does the טומאה tumah,
*tumah* status end by a נזיר nazir, *nazir*? He shaves and brings
a קרבן *korban*. אף ימי חלוטו מגלח ומביא קרבן *Af y'mei chaluto
m'gale'ach u'meivi korban*, so when you're מצורע metzora *metzora*, it's analogous, you
shave and you bring a קרבן *korban*. So therefore ומה ימי טומאה
tumah? אין עולין לו מן המנין *u'ma y'mei tumah ein olin lo
min haminyan*, so the same way when a נזיר nazir, *nazir* is
טמא *tamei*, it doesn't count, אף ימי חלוטו *af y'mei chaluto*, so
this period about being a מצורע metzora, *metzora*, you know on the
surface level looks very similar, also say אין עולין לו מן המנין
*ein olin lo min haminyan*, it doesn't count. Of course that's completely
bizarre cause one is, you know, within the laws of נזירות neziros,
*nezirut* so it's more deeply in conflict. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
לא *lo*, no. אם אמרת amarta,
בימי טומאה tumah. *Im amarta b'y'mei tumah*, I can say that when
the guy is a נזיר טמא nazir tamei *nazir tamei* that doesn't
count towards his thirty days שכן מבטל בהן את הקודמין *she'ken m'vatel
bahen et hakodmin*, because that's a really powerful he became טמא מת
*tamei meit* and the טמא מת *tamei meit* was so powerful that
it destroyed the earlier days. So of course you're not going to
be able to count these days. You're dealing with a state that's
antithetical to being a נזיר. nazir, So of course you know you've
lost the earlier days and of course you're not counting these days.
לפיכך אינם עולים מן המנין. lefikach einam olim min haminyan. That's why
a נזיר טמא nazir tamei? the days don't count. תאמר בימי חלוטו,
tomar bimei chaluto, how could you say the same thing by a
מצורע? metzora שאינו מבטל את הקודמים. she'eino mevatel es hakedomim. Being a
מצורע metzora, is not antithetical to being a נזיר טהור. nazir tahor.
You don't lose the earlier days. That's the proof. And since you
didn't lose the earlier days, לפיכך עולים מן המנין, lefikach olim min
haminyan, I'll say it's completely unrelated, completely orthogonal, and therefore it has
nothing to do with being a נזיר Nazir and you can even
count them. So that's a pretty good, pretty good argument, right? Why
should I ever think that being a מצורע metzora, has any effect
on being a נזיר, nazir. even to put it on hiatus? So
the ברייתא, Baraisa let's see how the ברייתא Baraisa continues.
אמרת, no, here's what you could say. ומה נזיר בקבר, umah nazir
bakever, let's look at this case. Somebody who was a נזיר Nazir
when they were in the
graveyard. Okay, our משנה. ששיערו ראוי
לתגלחת, she'searo raui letiglachas, his hair is fit for being shaved, אינו
עולה לו מן המנין, eino oleh lo min haminyan, and nevertheless the
days that he's a נזיר Nazir in the graveyard does not count
towards the thirty days. ימי חלוטו, the days that he's sealed up,
שאין ראוי לתגלחת, she'ein raui letiglachas, which are not fit for shaving,
לא כל שכן, lo kol shekein, how much more so should they,
should that not count. So what the heck does this mean, the
hair fit for shaving, and how is this relevant for counting or
not counting? So the גמרא is going to have two interpretations of
this. Okay, so let's read the, so we'll read the interpretations and
then we'll, and then we'll go back and explain what it means.
מאי
לאו תגלחת טומאה. mai lav tiglachas tumah. So when we say fit
for shaving, we, do we not mean shaving as the shaving that's
done for a נזיר טמא? nazir tamei, So how would that read?
It would read the guy in the, the נזיר בקבר, nazir bakever,
okay, שיערו ראוי לתגלחת she'searo raui letiglachas means we're going to shave
his hair as a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei okay, meaning that's the
question we're asking, the guy who took the vow and became a
נזיר in the בית הקברות, beis hakevaros, when it comes day seven,
no קרבן, are we going to shave his hair or not to
restart it? So the way the גמרא is reading this is that
it's assuming yes we will shave his hair. So it says, and
here's the argument about comparing the נזיר to the מצורע, metzora, to
the guy who's טמא to the guy who's a מצורע. metzora The
נזיר in the בית הקברות, beis hakevaros, what are we going to
do to restart his נזירות טהרה? nezirus taharah? We're going to shave
his hair. Okay, even though he took נזירות neziros in the בית
הקברות. Beis Hakvarot, The מצורע, metzora to restart his, to sort of
be able to sort of restart, there's no shaving of hair to
in order to restart a נזירות. neziros Now of course you could
say but wait a minute, there is a shaving of hair to
not be a מצורע. metzora Okay, that might be true. But there's
no shaving of hair about getting the נזירות neziros back on track.
All right? So if by the נזיר טמא nazir tamei, there's a
shaving of hair to get the נזירות neziros back on track, the
argument is, and this might, you might have said the opposite, but
the argument is, so he's still really in the נזיר mode, this
guy who's a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei. he's still in the נזיר
mode because he's going to be shaving and he's still, there's a
relevant laws of נזירות neziros. that apply to him as a נזיר
טמא. nazir tamei, He's going to have to shave in order to
get back on track. And even though he's still in a נזיר
mode, the period doesn't count towards the נזירות. This guy who's a
מצורע metzora whose טומאה tumah, does not entail any נזירות laws that
are relevant is not so much in a נזירות mode and how
much more so should the days not count. Now that's a pretty
bizarre proof because saying he's in the נזיר mode you could just
as equally say and that's why his טומאה tumah, is more of
a contradiction to the נזירות, whereas a מצורע metzora, he's not in
the נזיר mode because it's completely unrelated and therefore it should not
create any problem. But anyway, that's how the גמרא is reading it.
It's reading it that we're talking about one guy's going to shave
as a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei. the other not. So if the
guy who's still called a נזיר, the days are on hiatus, the
guy who's not in a נזיר mode should not be. And look,
you see the assumption is, is that the guy who took נזירות
in the בית הקברות Beis Hakvarot, is going to have to shave.
That's what we brought that to prove. Okay, now that's interpretation one
in רב פפא. Rav Pappa. And the גמרא says, לא, תגלחת טהרה.
lo, tiglachas taharah. No, no, no, it's meaning the תגלחת to become,
to become at the end of the
period. And here's how you read it. Okay, the case by the
guy in the בית הקברות, Beis Hakvarot all right, now he doesn't
have to shave to start his thirty days. But the end of
the process of נזירות is going to end with what?
Shaving, right? The guy who is a מצורע, metzora okay, becoming sort
of טהור is going to end with shaving, that's sort of getting
rid of the טומאה, but there's no way, but he's not, meaning
it's a way of saying this guy who's a מצורע is like,
hold on let me just double check תוספות before I say this.
Ah, ah, no, it's better than that. Hold on. Oh it's better.
It's saying the exact opposite of what we were assuming. The guy
in the בית הקברות, Beis Hakvarot it's assuming that... He's going to
go seven days and start his thirty days and he's not going
to have to shave his hair, right? He's in the בית הקברות,
Beis Hakvarot but he just has to wait seven days. Day seven
he becomes טהור. He counts his thirty days. The hair that's on
his head right now is not going to have to be, is
going to be safe, and it's only going to be shaved at
the end of the process, right? You're with me? That's the case
of the נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei What I'm trying to figure out...
what, wait, wait, no, no. But we're trying to figure out what
the assumption of the ברייתא Baraisa. is. Now we're assuming that the
ברייתא is assuming you don't shave to begin with. So this guy
in the בית הקברות, his hair is fit to be shaved, meaning
at the end of the process. That hair is going to be
safe, the guy in the בית הקברות for now. Okay, the guy
who's a מצורע, his hair is not going to be shaved at
the end of his being a נזיר. I'm a מצורע right now,
I'm a נזיר, the hair growing on my head is not going
to be part of the end of the process of my נזירות
because it's going to have to be shaved to get me out
of being a נזיר, out of being a מצורע, right? You see
that difference? So now what we're saying is, again, so the argument
is, so the guy there, he is much more in the process
of, it's much less of a contradiction to his נזירות, right? Because
his hair is still
good. This hyper-focus on hair is amazing. Anyway, his hair is still
safe, so he's still more fully a נזיר, and nevertheless, that period
doesn't count his thirty days. The guy who's a מצורע, we're going
to lose his hair, that hair won't be able to be shaved,
so that's more of a contradiction to the idea of a נזירות
because his hair is going to be shaved before the end of
the process, so how much more so should the period not count?
Alright, that's the argument. So again, a little bit bizarre that the
loss of the hair puts you more in contradiction to the idea
of נזירות than טומאת מת, which is the other case. Yes.
Could we say even more strongly that because part of the process
of counting your נזירות is getting that hair to the
טהרה? Right, not.
Right, and I think that's a sharp way of saying it because
that gets to the question I raised which is, which comes up
from this, if you shave the hair at the end of day,
at the end of מצורע, how can you just count twenty more
days? You're not even going to have thirty, I mean, it's even
a bigger question, you're not going to have thirty days of hair
growth. Right. So that no, we have to end, we're going to
have to end because there's a class that starts here in three
minutes, so I just want to read, I just want to finish
this part of the גמרא and then we're going to end. הכי
נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that makes sense דאי סלקא דעתך תגלחת
טומאה, de-i salka daitach tiglachat tumah, because
if it was just talking about being טמא that the נזיר shaves
his head and the בית הקברות shaves his head for טומאה, but
not the מצורע doesn't shave it for טומאה, ימי חלוטו מי לא
בעי תגלחת. Yemei chaluto mi lo ba'ei tiglachat. Well, how could you
say that the מצורע doesn't shave his head for טומאה? The מצורע
does shave his head for טומאה. How could you even say there's
a difference? So it says לא תגלחת דנזירות קתני. lo tiglachat di-neziros
katani. No, no, no. That we should have made fine. We could
have said the נזיר טמא shaves his head to end נזירות of
טומאה, the מצורע doesn't do a shaving relating to נזירות. He's going
to do a shaving relating to being a מצורע, but not a
shaving relating to being a נזיר. So where we're right now is
we have this ברייתא which makes this fascinating question about can the,
how do we know the הלכה halacha is undebatable? We know that
a מצורע the days don't, are on hiatus, don't destroy the earlier
days but don't count. The ברייתא tries to figure it out and
it compares it by comparing shaving from the two cases. It's unclear
whether that comparison tells us that the נזיר who's in the בית
הקברות doesn't shave when he starts his second counting or he does
shave. There's two ways of reading that ברייתא. So we still don't
have the answer, when the נזיר needs to restart if he started
with טומאה, when he restarts on day seven do you have to
shave or not? We will continue with that tomorrow. Have a great
day.